in this video you will learn how you can
send Insurance claim approval alerts on
SMS automatically so guys if you're
running an insurance company or you are
working in an insurance company and you
want to notify your policy holders that
you have approved uh the claim of their
insurance this automation is for you
here we have created a Insurance claim
form for the policy holders with the
help of Google forms application in
place of Google forms you can use any
other form Builder as well and as in
when they are going to fill the form and
submit the application the data will be
saved in a separate Google spreadsheet
and after that you can review the data
and approve the claims and as you're are
going to update the status of the claim
as approved in the Google sheet SMS will
be delivered to the policy holders
automatically and for that we are going
to use tro application right and we are
going to connect Google forms and tro in
the trigger and action steps inside the
automation workflow let me show you
how so to set up this automation guys we
are using pav connect which is an
automation tool and this is the landing
page of pav connect and we have pasted
the same Link in the description as well
from here you can set up your free P
connect account and you will get free
automation tasks every month to test and
set up your automations so you can sign
up right now and after that you have to
sign in and reach the P connect product
and you will see the dashboard of P
connect like this and guys here you have
to create a workflow of automation for
that just click on this create workflow
button and here you can give a suitable
name to this workflow so I'm giving the
name here as
insurance
policies
claims
alert so after that you have to click on
Create and you can see this will be the
workflow page and here you will find
these two modules the trigger and the
actions so with the help of these two
modules we can set up this automation so
guys in the trigger you have to connect
the trigger application and in that
application the trigger event is going
to occur so the trigger event is the
event which is going to Kickstart this
workflow and the action would be the
consequence of the trigger or the
response towards the trigger right and
uh and that action is going to happen in
the action appc application so guys in
our use case the trigger would uh
application would be Google forms from
which we are receiving the claim
applications okay and the submission of
the form will act as the trigger so you
have to search for Google forms here
here it is
selected all right and in the trigger
event select this new response received
option all right and it will give you
this URL this is called as WB hook URL
guys and with the help of this this we
can make a connection with any external
application and bring the data from that
application to here in this workflow so
guys to get the data here first you need
to make the connection uh with the
Google sheet attached with the Google
form okay so in every Google form uh
there is a spreadsheet attached in which
the data from the form is collected okay
I can show you that this is the form I
have created named as insurance claim
application form and the responses of
the form submissions are saving in this
spreadsheet you can see this is the
respons sheet so we need to connect this
spreadsheet with the workflow and then
we are going to capture the data of the
form response here right and you need to
follow these instructions to do that so
you can just read one by one and follow
them I'll show you directly how you can
do it so guys this is the spreadsheet in
which I'm receiving the form responses
and here you will find this extension
option click on extensions and you can
notice I have opened this spreadsheet in
an incognit window uh that's because I'm
using multiple Google accounts in the
same browser so if you are also doing
that it is better to open the
spreadsheet in incognito window so that
uh you won't face any issue in
connection okay right so here I'm
clicking on extensions and from this
add-on section click on get add-ons and
from this Google workspace Marketplace
you have to install an add-on here which
is called P connect web hooks so you
just have to search for p connect web
hooks here p a BBL l y p connect web
Hooks and you have to install it here so
it will just take 2 minutes and it will
be installed as I have already installed
it here I do not to do it again and
after installing that add-on remember to
refresh the spreadsheet okay by clicking
here refresh the spreadsheet and after
that when you click on extensions you
will find this P connect vbox option
available in here in the drop down from
here you have to click on initial setup
and under initial setup you will find
these two Fields the wab hook URL field
and the trigger column field okay so in
the VAB URL field let me erase this
first in the VB URL field you have to
paste the wook URL that you got from
your workflow and in the trigger column
you have to uh enter the enter the last
or the final data entry column of your
spreadsheet Okay so our trigger column
will be this F
column okay here the as the data is
going to enter here in the F column the
workflow should trigger and start
working
right so after getting the responses
here we are going to check the responses
and manually approve or disapprove the
application okay okay so after approving
or dis approving we are going to send
the alert SMS but before this the
trigger should start working as we got
the data right so for this click on
extensions oh sorry first of all let us
copy the webook URL that you got that we
got here in the workflow just click on
copy from
here and here you can see started
showing waiting for the response okay
this means now we can bring the test
data here test data means a data of a
row from the spreadsheet from the
responsive spreadsheet to here and with
the help of that data we are going to
move forward in the automation okay so
uh you have to manually fill the form to
get the data here then we can bring it
in the workflow okay so you can fill
some demo details or the dummy details
and uh just to set up this automation to
get the test data
right uh so here is my spreadsheet click
on extensions and here is p connect
books initial
setup here let me erase this field and
paste the wab URL okay and here we have
the send test button so when you click
on send test the data of the first row
that I have will be sent to the workflow
as the test data right so I'm clicking
on send
test and here we can see the test data
has send successfully is written here
okay now you can click on
submit and close this window now let's
check in our workflow if we got the
data and here you can see we got the
test data captured like this from this
insurance claim application this is the
whole data the policy number the row
index is two that is the data is coming
from second row a phone number full name
email address these are the questions I
have asked from the policy beneficiaries
here in the form and the data got
captured here in the workflow right now
guys uh after receiving the applications
from the policy holders and let me show
you one thing more in the spreadsheet
from this extensions go to P connect
vbook option one more time and here
click on send on event button also so
when you click on send on event whenever
you are going to receive a form
submission the workflow is going to
trigger okay right so come back to the
workflow and what I'm seeing here uh
that when you receive the form
applications a person manually check the
details received in the form okay and
after that here in this application
status uh column we have two options
approve you can see approve or
disapprove so whenever the person is
going to click on approve manually then
we want to send the sms okay so let's
say it took uh one day to check all the
applications and uh approve or
disapprove the applications so we want
that after getting the data getting all
the details here in the spreadsheet our
work flow should stop for a day for 24
hours so that we can mention the
application statuses here and after that
we are going to send the alert SMS to
only those applicants whose applications
we have approved right so guys for that
to Hal this workflow after this step for
24 hours we are going to apply the delay
here so with the help of this delay
feature or delay module of ab you can uh
put a halt on a workflow so here it is
asking how much delay you want to put in
a workflow so I'm going to uh select
delay for option and in the delay units
I'm going to select days and then the
delay value I just want to put the delay
of one day okay so that we can check the
applications right so click on Save and
send test request and here you can see
the workflow is delayed for one day
right after that what we want we want
that this workflow should check the
application status and send the alert
messages to the people whose
applications are approved so for that we
are going to uh to check the uh
spreadsheet just click here on the on
this plus icon and we need to bring the
data again here from the spreadsheet so
connect with Google Sheets
again and in the action
event uh you can you can select look up
spreadsheet rows option okay select
lookup spreadsheet rows then click on
connect
and uh from here select add new
connection then click on connect with
Google Sheets and from here you have to
select the Google account by which you
have created that spreadsheet then you
have to provide some additional access
to your account just click on continue
that is completely save and you can see
the authorization is successful and you
we are going to be connected like this
with the spreadsheet right and here it
is asking to select the spreadsheets
name so my spreadsheets name is this
insurance claim applications so I'm
going to select from
here okay and then it will ask for
selecting the sheets name so we have two
sheets here and I'm working in this form
responses one sheet so I'm going to
select it from here okay now it is
asking uh where you want to look up for
a specific thing so with the help of
look up you can search for any value in
a specific column so I want to search uh
in the G column the approval the
application statuses okay and I want to
search for this approved term only so
just put capital G here and in the look
up value put approve and you have to
type approve in the capital A as it is
as you have mentioned here
okay okay now include headers yes and
start sorting the values from the top
yes then click on Save and send test
request and in the
responses this lookup spreadsheet uh
feature is going to capture the details
of all the people whose application
statuses are approved okay and here you
can see it is showing you the data like
this okay but right now I have only uh
one applicant here but you can many even
hundreds of applicants you can have in
the spreadsheet so we want to uh uh we
are going to take the details one by one
okay we are going to sort out the
details one by one and we are going to
send the alerts one by one to all the
applicants who whose application
statuses are approved starting from the
first person for that what we can do
here you have to toggle this simple
response button to off then capture the
details again click on Save and send one
more
time and here you can see now we got the
result in advanc format and here you can
see in this respon response result label
we got the data in this array format
right so now we can uh segregate this
array with the help of a feature of P
conet which is called iterator so what
iterator will do iterator will separate
out the values row by Row for those
people only whose application statuses
are approved okay and starting from the
first person then for second then for
third and it is going to make this
workflow run one by one for each person
so just click here on this plus icon and
search for iterator feature here it is
selected and here it is asking to choose
the array so we are going to choose this
response result array for that you just
have to click here and it will show you
the previous step like this from here
map this response result array then
click on Save and send test request
button and here you can see we got the
details of the first person whose
application is approved okay now we can
send the SMS and to send the SMS I'm
using twio application just click here
on this plus icon and connect twio here
which is a SMS sending platform in this
action
step and the action event would be send
SMS message click on connect from here
select add new connection and here it is
asking for the account Sid the token and
the Sid again so you'll find these three
things in your twio console like this so
you just have to click on this twio
account console and in the account info
section you will find the Sid just copy
that and paste it here two
times here and
here similarly you'll find the token
just copy that and paste it
here all right and after that click on
Save and you'll be connected with
twio right and here it is asking for the
body of the SMS so let me type a
standard message for my policy
holders so guys I have written a small
SMS for my policy holders you can change
this SMS according to you and here after
deer I want to place the name of the
person to whom I'm sending the SMS so
I'm going to map the name from the
previous step or from the Google form
trigger uh in which you can see in this
form I have asked for the name the email
address the policy number and all the
things and we got the data here and we
have captured the data here in the
trigger so here you can see when I'm
clicking here it is showing us the
previous uh step like this in the drop
down so from this Google form step I'm
going to map the data like this okay
right and
here you can read your insurance claim
against the policy number so here I'm
going to place the policy number from
the first step only here is the policy
number right and uh in the sender number
you will get the sender number from your
12 account here you can see this is the
trilo senders phone number you can just
copy it and paste it
here like this and in the recipient
number I'm going to map the number of
the insurance policy holder and you'll
get the number from the first step here
you can see the phone number label map
it okay now you can check your
connection by clicking on Save and send
test request and SMS will be delivered
to this number so this is not an actual
number guys so to show you the demo of
how how the SMS is going to look like I
am going to enter my number
here and after that I'm going to click
on Save and send test request and show
you the SMS so guys I have clicked on
Save and send test request and this is
the response we have received let me
show you the message on my phone and
here you can see this is the message I
have received and here you can read dear
demo name your insurance claim against
the policy number has been accepted and
we'll credit the amount to you in 3 days
so this is how it is going to work guys
and you can see in place of the uh name
as I have mapped the name here you can
see the data got placed in the message
accordingly that's why it is necessary
to map the data and every time the form
is going to be submitted and you are
going to approve the status these
details that you have mapped here are
going to change and a new m sms will be
sent to the new person okay and guys
remember to uh map this uh these values
from the iterator step not from the
trigger actually we are going to map it
from
iterator okay because we have separated
the data of only those people whose
details have approved from iterator so
remember to map these things from the
iterator step okay this number
also okay now we are done and now you
can save the step step and we are done
setting up this Automation and you have
to set up this automation only once
after that you don't have to do anything
manually after that whenever you are
going to approve the status or the form
is going to submitted this workflow is
going to run automatically and guys if
you want to use this workflow you can
use it because I'm going to paste the
link of this workflow in the description
and you can clone it in your own free P
connect
account guys thank you so much for
watching our video and please please let
us know how our automation ideas are
helping you in the comment section and
if you have any queries related to this
application please ask your queries from
this forum link and do check the pricing
of this application from this link and
guys we are open to ideas if you want us
that we should make videos on other
aspects of your business please do let
us know in the comment section and if
you like our work please subscribe to
our Channel